Design is a slippery and elusive phenomenon,
التصميم ظاهرة غامضة وصعبة المنال،
which has meant different things at different times.
حظيت بمعان مختلفة وبأزمان مختلفة.
But all truly inspiring design projects have one thing in common:
لكن تتشارك جميع مشاريع التصميم المثيرة بشيء واحد:
they began with a dream.
تبدأ بحلم.
And the bolder the dream,
وكلما زادت جرأة الحلم،
the greater the design feat that will be required to achieve it.
ازداد تفرد التصميم المطلوب تحقيقه.
And this is why the greatest designers are almost always
ولهذا السبب فإن المصممين العظماء هم عادةَ تقريباَ
the biggest dreamers and rebels and renegades.
أكبر الحالمين والمتمردين والمارقين.
This has been the case throughout history,
وهذا هو الحال على مدى التاريخ،
all the way back to the year 300 BC,
بالعودة لسنة 300 قبل الميلاد،
when a 13-year-old became the king
عندما أصبح فتى بعمر 13 عاماً ملكاَ
of a remote, very poor and very small Asian country.
على بلد آسيوي ناء صغير وفقير جداً.
He dreamt of acquiring land, riches and power
فقد حلم بالاستيلاء على الأرض، وخيراتها وطاقاتها
through military conquest.
من خلال الفتوحات العسكرية.
And his design skills --
ومهاراته في التصميم--
improbable though it sounds --
غير المتوقعة على ما يبدو--
would be essential in enabling him to do so.
كانت أساسية لتمكنه من تحقيق ذلك.
At the time,
وفي ذلك الوقت،
all weapons were made by hand to different specifications.
كانت الأسلحة تصنع يدوياً وبمواصفات مختلفة.
So if an archer ran out of arrows during a battle,
لذا إن نفدت الأسهم من أحد الرماة خلال المعركة،
they wouldn't necessarily be able to fire another archer's arrows
فمن غير الضروري ان يتمكن من استخدام سهام رام آخر
from their bow.
من قوسه.
This of course meant that they would be less effective in combat
ويعني هذا بالطبع أنهم سيكونون أقل فاعلية في المعركة
and very vulnerable, too.
وأكثر ضعفاَ أيضاً.
Ying solved this problem
قام ينغ بحل تلك المشكلة
by insisting that all bows and arrows were designed identically,
من خلال الإصرار على تصميم الأقواس والسهام كافة بشكل متماثل،
so they were interchangeable.
و أصبحت بذلك قابلة للتبادل.
And he did the same for daggers, axes, spears, shields
وأصر على نفس الأمر بالنسبة للخناجر والفؤوس والرماح والدروع
and every other form of weaponry.
وكل أشكال الأسلحة الأخرى.
His formidably equipped army won batter after battle,
وانتصر جيشه المجهز تجهيزاً لا يقهر في المعركة تلو الأخرى،
and within 15 years,
وفي غضون 15 عاماَ،
his tiny kingdom had succeeded in conquering
نجحت مملكته الصغيرة جداً في الاستيلاء
all its larger, richer, more powerful neighbors,
على كل البلدان المجاورة الأكبر والأغنى والأقوى،
to found the mighty Chinese Empire.
ليؤسس الإمبراطورية الصينية العظيمة.
Now, no one, of course,
والآن، لا أحد، بالطبع،
would have thought of describing Ying Zheng as a designer at the time --
يخطر بباله وصف يينغ تزينغ بالمصمم في زمانه--
why would they?
ولم يصفونه؟
And yet he used design unknowingly and instinctively
وعلى الرغم من ذلك استخدم التصميم دون دراية وعفوياً
but with tremendous ingenuity
ولكن بعبقرية هائلة
to achieve his ends.
لتحقيق أهدافه.
And so did another equally improbable, accidental designer,
وعلى نفس المنوال مصمم آخر غير محتمل وبالصدفة،
who was also not above using violence to get what he wanted.
والذي أيضاَ لم يستخدم العنف لتحقيق مناله.
This was Edward Teach, better known as the British pirate, Blackbeard.
إنه إدوارد تيتش، الذي يشتهر باسم القرصان البريطاني، بلاكبيرد.
This was the golden age of piracy,
وكان ذلك العصر الذهبي للقرصنة،
where pirates like Teach were terrorizing the high seas.
عندما كان يرهب القراصنة كأمثال تيتش أعالي البحار.
Colonial trade was flourishing,
كانت تزدهر التجارة بين المستعمرات
and piracy was highly profitable.
وكانت القرصنة تحقق أرباحاً عالية.
And the smarter pirates like him realized that to maximize their spoils,
والقراصنة الأذكياء كأمثاله أدركوا ذلك لمضاعفة غنائمهم،
they needed to attack their enemies so brutally
كان عليهم مهاجمة أعدائهم بوحشية كبيرة
that they would surrender on sight.
بحيث يستسلمون بمجرد رؤية القراصنة.
So in other words,
لذا بعبارة أخرى،
they could take the ships without wasting ammunition,
كانوا يستولون على السفن دون إضاعة الذخيرة،
or incurring casualties.
أو تكبد الخسائرالبشرية.
So Edward Teach redesigned himself as Blackbeard
لذا أعاد إدوارد تيتش تصميم شخصه ليصبح بلاك بيرد
by playing the part of a merciless brute.
من خلال لعب دور الغاشم الذي لا يرحم.
He wore heavy jackets and big hats to accentuate his height.
كان يرتدي الستر الثقيلة والقبعات الكبيرة لإبراز طول قامته.
He grew the bushy black beard that obscured his face.
وأطلق لحيته الكثيفة السوداء التي حجبت وجهه.
He slung braces of pistols on either shoulder.
وعلق على كل كتف حمالة سلاح.
He even attached matches to the brim of his hat and set them alight,
حتى أنه ألصق أعواد الثقاب حول حواف قبعته وأشعلها،
so they sizzled menacingly whenever his ship was poised to attack.
لذا تتوهج مهددة عندما تأخذ السفينة وضعية الهجوم.
And like many pirates of that era,
وكالعديد من القراصنة إبان تلك الفترة،
he flew a flag that bore the macabre symbols
رفع علماً يحمل صوراً مروعة
of a human skull and a pair of crossed bones,
لجمجمة بشرية تتصالب أمامها عظمتان،
because those motifs had signified death in so many cultures for centuries,
كون هذه الرموز كانت تشير للموت في العديد من الحضارات عبر القرون،
that their meaning was instantly recognizable,
وأن معناها كان ملحوظاً بشكل مباشر،
even in the lawless, illiterate world of the high seas:
حتى في عالم أعالي البحار الفوضوي والجاهل:
surrender or you'll suffer.
استسلم وإلا ستعاني.
So of course, all his sensible victims surrendered on sight.
لذا بالطبع استسلم كل ضحاياه المذعورون لدى رؤيته.
Put like that,
وضع من هذا القبيل،
it's easy to see why Edward Teach and his fellow pirates
من السهولة فهم لما يمكن رؤية إدوارد تيتش ورفاقه القراصنة
could be seen as pioneers of modern communications design,
كرواد تصميم الاتصالات الحديثة،
and why their deadly symbol --
ولما كان رمزهم المميت--
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
there's more --
هنالك المزيد--
why their deadly symbol of the skull and crossbones
لما كان رمزهم المميت من خلال الجمجمة والعظمتين المتقاطعتين
was a precursor of today's logos,
تمهيداَ لشعارات هذه الأيام،
rather like the big red letters standing behind me,
كالأحرف الحمراء الكبيرة التي تقف خلفي،
but of course with a different message.
لكن طبعاً برسالة مختلفة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Yet design was also used to nobler ends
ومع ذلك ،استخدم التصميم لغايات أنبل
by an equally brilliant and equally improbable designer,
من قبل مصممين رائعين و غير متوقعين على التساوي،
the 19th-century British nurse, Florence Nightingale.
الممرضة البريطانية في القرن 19 فلورنس نايتنغيل.
Her mission was to provide decent healthcare for everyone.
كانت مهمتها توفير الرعاية الصحية اللائقة للجميع.
Nightingale was born into a rather grand, very wealthy British family,
ولدت نايتنغيل لعائلة بريطانية نبيلة ثرية جداَ،
who were horrified when she volunteered to work in military hospitals
أصيبت عائلتها بالذعر عند تطوعها للعمل في المشافي العسكرية
during the Crimean War.
خلال حرب القرم.
Once there, she swiftly realized
فعندما وصلت هناك، أدركت بسرعة
that more patients were dying of infections that they caught there,
أن العديد من المرضى يموتون بسبب العدوى التي تصيبهم هناك،
in the filthy, fetid wards,
في الأجنحة القذرة والنتنة،
than they were of battle wounds.
أكثر من تبعات إصابات الحرب.
So she campaigned for cleaner, lighter, airier clinics
لذا أطلقت حملة لعيادات أنظف و أكثر إنارة و تهوية
to be designed and built.
لكي يتم تصميمها و بنائها.
Back in Britain,
بالعودة لبريطانيا،
she mounted another campaign,
أطلقت حملة أخرى،
this time for civilian hospitals,
وهذه المرة للمشافي المدنية،
and insisted that the same design principles were applied to them.
وأصرت على تطبيق مبادئ التصميم ذاتها.
The Nightingale ward, as it is called,
جناح نايتنغيل، كما أطلق عليه،
dominated hospital design for decades to come,
هيمن على تصميم المشافي لعشرات السنين التالية،
and elements of it are still used today.
ولا تزال بعض عناصره قيد الاستخدام لليوم.
But by then,
ولكن في ذلك الوقت،
design was seen as a tool of the Industrial Age.
كان التصميم يرى كأداة من أدوات العصر الصناعي.
It was formalized and professionalized,
قد تم تشكيله ووضع حرفيته،
but it was restricted to specific roles
ولكن اقتصر على أدوار معينة
and generally applied in pursuit of commercial goals
وكان يطبق عموماً ضمن السعي لتحقيق أهدافاً تجارية
rather than being used intuitively,
أكثرمن استعماله بديهياً،
as Florence Nightingale, Blackbeard and Ying Zheng had done.
كما فعل كل من فلورنس نايتنغيل، وبلاك بيرد، وينغ تزينغ.
By the 20th century,
وبحلول القرن العشرين،
this commercial ethos was so powerful,
كانت الروح التجارية قوية جداً،
that any designers who deviated from it
لدرجة أن أي مصمم يحيد عنها
risked being seen as cranks or subversives.
يخاطر بالنظر إليه كأحد المهووسين أو المخربين.
Now among them is one of my great design heroes,
ومن بين هؤلاء يبرز أحد أعظم أبطال التصميم،
the brilliant László Moholy-Nagy.
الرائع لازلو موهولي - ناج.
He was the Hungarian artist and designer
كان الفنان والمصمم الهنغاري
whose experiments with the impact of technology on daily life
التي كانت تجاربه حول تأثير التكنولوجيا على الحياة اليومية
were so powerful
قوية جداً
that they still influence the design of the digital images
لدرجة أنها ما تزال تؤثر على تصميم الصور الرقمية
we see on our phone and computer screens.
التي نراها على شاشات هواتفنا وحواسيبنا.
He radicalized the Bauhaus Design School in 1920s Germany,
حوّل مدرسة باوهاوس الألمانية للتصميم في عشرينيات القرن الماضي لمدرسة رادكالية،
and yet some of his former colleagues shunned him
حتى تجنبه بعض زملاءه السابقين
when he struggled to open a new Bauhaus in Chicago years later.
عندما ناضل لافتتاح مدرسة باهوس في شيكاغو بعد سنوات.
Moholy's ideas were as bold and incisive as ever,
كانت أفكار موهولي أفكاراً جريئة ثاقبة البصر أكثر من غيرها على الإطلاق،
but his approach to design was too experimental,
لكن منهجه في التصميم كان منهجاً تجريبياً للغاية،
as was his insistence on seeing it, as he put it,
كما كان تصميميه على رؤيته، كما وضعه،
as an attitude, not a profession to be in tune with the times.
كسلوك، لا يمثل سلوكاَ مهنياَ متناغماَ مع باقي الأزمان.
And sadly, the same applied
وللاسف، ينطبق الأمر نفسه
to another design maverick: Richard Buckminster Fuller.
على مصمم مستقل آخر: ريتشارد بوكمنستر فيولر.
He was yet another brilliant design visionary
كان مصمماَ آخراَ لامعاَ في التصميم التخيلي
and design activist,
وتصميم الأحداث،
who was completely committed to designing a sustainable society
إذ أنه التزم التزاماً كاملاً بتصميم المجتمع المستدام
in such a forward-thinking way
كطريقة للتفكير المتقدم
that he started talking about the importance of environmentalism
حيث أنه بدأ بالتحدث عن أهمية حماية البيئة
in design in the 1920s.
في التصميم في عشرينيات القرن الماضي.
Now he, despite his efforts,
والأن، بالرغم من جهوده،
was routinely mocked as a crank by many in the design establishment,
سخر منه العديد من مؤسسة التصميم،
and admittedly,
وباعتراف الجميع،
some of his experiments failed,
فشلت بعض تجاربه،
like the flying car that never got off the ground.
كالسيارة الطائرة التي لم تغادر الأرض على الإطلاق.
And yet, the geodesic dome,
ومع ذلك، فالقبة الجيوديسية،
his design formula to build an emergency shelter
وصيغة تصميمه لبناء ملجإ الطوارئ
from scraps of wood, metal, plastic,
من بقايا الأخشاب، والمعادن، والبلاستيك،
bits of tree, old blankets, plastic sheeting --
وقطع الأشجار، والبطانيات القديمة، الأغطية البلاستيكية
just about anything that's available at the time --
وأي شيء متوفر في ذلك الوقت--
is one of the greatest feats of humanitarian design,
هو واحد من أعظم المفاخر في التصميم الإنساني،
and has provided sorely needed refuge
وقد وفر ذلك للاجئين ذوي الحاجة الماسة
to many, many people in desperate circumstances
وللعديد العديد ممن يمر بظروف يائسة
ever since.
آنذاك.
Now, it was the courage and verve of radical designers
والآن، كانت شجاعة وحيوية المصممين المتمردين
like Bucky and Moholy
مثل بكي وماهولي
that drew me to design.
التي دفعتني للتصميم.
I began my career as a news journalist and foreign correspondent.
بدأت مهنتي كصحفية اخبار ومراسلة أجنبية.
I wrote about politics, economics and corporate affairs,
كنت أكتب حول السياسة، والاقتصاد، وشؤون الشركات،
and I could have chosen to specialize in any of those fields.
وكان بإمكاني أن أتخصص في أحد تلك الاختصاصات.
But I picked design,
لكني اخترت التصميم،
because I believe it's one of the most powerful tools at our disposal
لانني اؤمن بأنه من أقوى الوسائل في حوزتنا
to improve our quality of life.
لتحسين جودة حياتنا.
Thank you, fellow TED design buffs.
شكرا لكم، الزملاء هواة التصميم في TED
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And greatly as I admire the achievements of professional designers,
وبنفس القدر الكبير من الإعجاب بإنجازات المصممين المحترفين،
which have been extraordinary and immense,
والتي كانت استثنائية وهائلة،
I also believe
أؤمن أيضاً
that design benefits hugely from the originality,
أن التصميم يستفيد بشكل هائل من الأصالة،
the lateral thinking
والتفكير الجانبي
and the resourcefulness of its rebels and renegades.
ودهاء المتمردين والمارقين.
And we're living at a remarkable moment in design,
ونحن نعيش في لحظات مميزة في التصميم.
because this is a time when the two camps are coming closer together.
لأن هذا هو الوقت الذي يتقارب فيه كلا المعسكران سويةً.
Because even very basic advances in digital technology
لأنه حتى التقدمات الاساسية في التكنولوجيا الرقمية
have enabled them to operate increasingly independently,
قد مكنتهما من العمل بشكل متزايد باستقلالية،
in or out of a commercial context,
سواء في السياق التجاري أم خارجه،
to pursue ever more ambitious and eclectic objectives.
لتحقيق أهداف أكثر طموحاً وانتقائيةً.
So in theory,
لذا نظرياً،
basic platforms like crowdfunding, cloud computing, social media
المنصات الأساسية كالتمويل الجماعي،الحوسبة السحابية، وسائل التواصل الاجتماعي
are giving greater freedom to professional designers
تقدم حريةً أكبر للمصميمن المحترفين
and giving more resources for the improvisational ones,
وتقدم مصادر اكثر للمصممين الارتجاليين،
and hopefully,
ونأمل،
a more receptive response to their ideas.
في استجابة أكثر تقبلاً لأفكارهم.
Now, some of my favorite examples of this are in Africa,
والآن، بعض الأمثلة المفضلة لدي في هذه المنطقة من إفريقيا،
where a new generation of designers
إذ أن جيلاً جديداً من المصممين
are developing incredible Internet of Things technologies
يطورون تقنيات لا تصدق في تقنيات إنترنت الأشياء
to fulfill Florence Nightingale's dream of improving healthcare
لتحقيق حلم فلورنس نايتنغيل في تحسين الرعاية الصحية
in countries where more people now have access to cell phones
في بلدان أصبح العديد من الناس قادرين على الحصول على الهواتف المحمولة
than to clean, running water.
أكثر من حصولهم على الماء النظيف و الجاري.
And among them is Arthur Zang.
ومن بينهم آرثر زانق.
He's a young, Cameroonian design engineer
إنه مهندس تصميم كاميروني شاب
who has a adapted a tablet computer into the Cardiopad,
وهو الذي عدل الكمبيوتر اللوحي إلى جهاز الأمراض القلبية،
a mobile heart-monitoring device.
وهو جهاز نقال يراقب القلب.
It can be used to monitor the hearts of patients in remote, rural areas.
يمكن استخدامه لمراقبة قلوب المرضى في المناطق الريفية النائية.
The data is then sent on a cellular network
ترسل البيانات عبر الشبكة الخليوية
to well-equipped hospitals hundreds of miles away
إلى المشافي المجهزة تجهيزاً مناسباً على بعد مئات الأميال
for analysis.
بغية تحليلها.
And if any problems are spotted by the specialists there,
وإن تم تحديد أي مشكلة من قبل المختص هناك،
a suitable course of treatment is recommended.
يتم التوصية ببرنامج علاجي ملائم.
And this of course saves many patients
ويوفر هذا البرنامج على العديد من المرضى
from making long, arduous, expensive and often pointless journeys
الرحلات الطويلة والشاقة والباهظة التكلفة وغير الضرورية
to those hospitals,
إلى تلك المشافي،
and makes it much, much likelier
ويجعلها أكثر احتمالاً
that their hearts will actually be checked.
بأن يتم فحص قلوبهم فعلياً.
Arthur Zang started working on the Cardiopad eight years ago,
بدأ آرثر زانق العمل على الجهاز قبل ثمان سنوات،
in his final year at university.
في السنة الأخيرة له في الجامعة.
But he failed to persuade any conventional sources
لكنه فشل في إقناع أي من المصادر التقليدية
to give him investment to get the project off the ground.
لتقديم التمويل اللازم للنهوض بالمشروع.
He posted the idea on Facebook,
عرض الفكرة على الفيسبوك،
where a Cameroonian government official saw it
حيث رآها أحد المسؤولين الكاميرونين الحكوميين
and managed to secure a government grant for him.
وتمكن من تأمين منحة حكومية له.
He's now developing not only the Cardiopad,
والآن لا يقوم بتطوير جهاز مراقبة القلب وحسب،
but other mobile medical devices to treat different conditions.
بل أجهزة طبية متنقلة أخرى لمعالجة الحالات المختلفة.
And he isn't alone,
وهو ليس وحيداً،
because there are many other inspiring and enterprising designers
لأن هنالك العديد من المصممين الملهمين والمغامرين
who are also pursuing extraordinary projects of their own.
ممن يسعون لإنجاز مشاريعهم غير العادية.
And I'm going to finish by looking at just a few of them.
وسأنهي حديثي بالنظر إلى البعض فقط منهم.
One is Peek Vision.
أحدهم بيك فيجن.
This is a group of doctors and designers in Kenya,
وهي مجموعة من الأطباء والمصممين في كينيا،
who've developed an Internet of Things technology of their own,
ممن طوروا تكنولوجيا إنترنت الأشياء الخاصة بهم،
as a portable eye examination kit.
كعلبة الفحص العينية المحمولة.
Then there's Gabriel Maher,
وثم هناك جبريل ماهر،
who is developing a new design language
وهو يطور لغة تصميم جديدة
to enable us to articulate the subtleties of our changing gender identities,
لنتمكن من توضيح خفايا هوياتنا الجنسية المتغيرة،
without recourse to traditional stereotypes.
دون اللجوء للأنماط التقليدية.
All of these designers and many more are pursuing their dreams,
كل أولئك المصممون وغيرهم الكثير يسعون لتحقيق أحلامهم،
by the making the most of their newfound freedom,
من خلال الاستفادة القصوى من حرياتهم المكتشفة حديثاً،
with the discipline of professional designers
ومن انضباط المصممين المحترفين
and the resourcefulness of rebels and renegades.
ودهاء المتمردين والمارقين.
And we all stand to benefit.
ونحن جميعا ننتظر كي نستفيد.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)